<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>New To Life</title><link href="http://www.newtolife.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.newtolife.net/feeds/newtolife.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.newtolife.net/</id><updated>2015-09-25T12:23:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>1 month of BJJ training in Rio</title><link href="http://www.newtolife.net/1-month-of-bjj-training-in-rio.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-09-25T12:23:00+02:00</updated><author><name>newtolife</name></author><id>tag:www.newtolife.net,2015-09-25:1-month-of-bjj-training-in-rio.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Açaí" src="http://www.newtolife.net/images/bjj_rio/acai.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Açaí)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Intro&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi. I recently came back from a 2 months trip to Brazil (7-8/2015). On the
first month I was doing some &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brazilian_jiu-jitsu"&gt;Brazilian Jiu
Jitsu&lt;/a&gt; in Rio de Janeiro. I
want to tell you about the experience, and provide you some useful information
if you ever want to do this yourself. While the phenomenon of strangers coming
to Brazil for BJJ (Brazilian Jiu Jitsu) is not something new, it is still
somewhat difficult to find information online about how to do it properly. I
thought I can add my 1 month of knowledge here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This document is by no means an official guide. It contains mostly my opinion
about things, and may also contain wrong or outdated facts. Make sure to
doublecheck anything before relying on this information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For any questions or suggestions you are more than welcome to mail me at
thenewtolife(&amp;amp;)outlook.com. (Just replace the &amp;amp; with a @).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;About myself&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was born in 1987. I am not a very experienced BJJ fighter. I started my BJJ
trainings somewhere in 2014, about 1 year ago, and I still proudly wear my white
belt. My main background in martial arts is Judo. I currently own a blue belt,
and I am training for about 24 years, probably since 1991.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judo has mainly two parts for the fight: The standing part, where the main goal
is to throw people to the ground and win points, and the ground part 
(&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grappling#Ground_grappling"&gt;newaza&lt;/a&gt;), where you
are supposed to hold your opponent back to the ground for long enough time, or
apply some submission like a choke or an armbar. In the judo clubs where I was
trained, the standing game was the main part, and ground game took only about
20% or even less from the total time of training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn't know about BJJ until recently. Being an innocent Judoka I believed for
many years that my ground game was really good. It rarely happened to me that I
met another Judoka that won me on the ground. In competitions, people always
tried to avoid spending time with me on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On my &lt;a href="http://www.newtolife.net/2-months-of-training-at-the-kodokan.html"&gt;stay at the kodokan&lt;/a&gt; I met a few guys that
beat me really hard on the ground. I had to ask where did the learn this kind of
Judo, and they answered that it's not Judo, it's BJJ. Coming back home from
Japan I found a good BJJ academy and started training. After about one year I
decided to check out how Brazilian Jiu Jitsu looks like at the origin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Some history&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don't have to be a genius to see that there is some relation between Judo
and BJJ. They have somewhat the same kimonos (Although the BJJ ones are a bit
more colorful, one must admit), and the main rules are similar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the beginning of the 20th century Kano Jigoro, the founder of
Judo, has sent few Judokas to spread the art of Judo overseas. One of those
Judokas was &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mitsuyo_Maeda"&gt;Mitsuyo Maeda&lt;/a&gt;, which
was also known to be a judo groundwork expert. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maeda has arrived to Brazil in 1914 and started teaching Judo to his first
Brazilian students. A notable student was &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carlos_Gracie"&gt;Carlos
Gracie&lt;/a&gt;, which also continued to
teach the art to his siblings. His brother, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/H%C3%A9lio_Gracie"&gt;Hélio
Gracie&lt;/a&gt; continued to develop an
art called the Gracie Jiu Jitsu, an adaptation of Judo that focused on ground
work, because he was not able to perform judo moves that required direct
strength against the opponent. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another school of Judo in Brazil originated from &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geo_Omori"&gt;Geo
Omori&lt;/a&gt;, a Japanese that opened the
first Judo school in Brazil in 1909. One of his notable students was &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luiz_Fran%C3%A7a"&gt;Luiz
França&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new form of groundwork based Judo in Brazil has evolved over the years to
what is called today Brazilian Jiu Jitsu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that BJJ is not the same as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jujutsu"&gt;Jiu
Jitsu&lt;/a&gt;, which is a pretty old Japanese
martial art. The correct order of things would be: Jiu Jitsu -&amp;gt; Judo -&amp;gt;
Brazilian Jiu Jitsu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;A place to train and a place to sleep&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding a good BJJ academy to train and a place to stay were my first priorities
when planning the trip to Rio. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most websites mention &lt;a href="http://www.connectionrio.com/"&gt;ConnectionRio&lt;/a&gt; as a place
to stay together with likely minded BJJ fighters. I eventually didn't stay there
because there weren't available double rooms at the time (I came to Rio with my
girlfriend, she is probably not dorms material). I did have the opportunity to
talk to Dennis Asche from ConnectionRio over mail and he seemed to be a great
guy. If I was arriving to Rio by myself I would have probably chosen to stay at
the dorms at ConnectionRio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I searched the web for active BJJ academies around Rio. Some academies that were
mentioned by many are Academia Gracie, Terere Academy, Gracie Tijuca, Academia
Gordo and Equipe Fabricio Jiu Jitsu. You can see them here, on the map:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/d/embed?mid=zSWPS0CFAI0M.kseH1z5zmEME" 
width="640" height="480"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I assumed that any of those academies would be good enough for a beginner like
myself, so it was just about finding a place to stay in a good location which is
close enough to one of those academies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I considered staying at a hostel somewhere nearby, but I found out that hostels
around Rio could be pretty expensive. In addition, I came to the conclusion that
a hostel doesn't have the facilities needed for a person that trains twice a
day. I also thought about renting a place in Rio, however without any local help
I realized that it might take a while before I managed to find a good deal, and
I didn't have much time to waste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I heard about &lt;a href="https://www.airbnb.com/"&gt;Airbnb&lt;/a&gt; as a good method of renting a
place for short periods of time. I managed to find a pretty nice apartment
through Airbnb which was 3 minutes walk from Equipe Fabricio Jiu Jitsu Academy.
I paid for it 1500 US dollars (Including airbnb's commission and all the other
expenses). It was an apartment suitable for 2 people, it included a working
laundry machine (Very important if you are training a lot!) and a guard at the
entrance. Note that it was a pretty fancy choice. You can probably find a
cheaper apartment if you show up alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, I think this apartment was the best thing I could do with my money
with respect to accommodation. It felt pretty safe (The building had a personal
guard!), I could make my own food at the kitchen, clean my clothes using the
laundry machine, and wake up 20 minutes before the morning training starts,
without having to worry about being late. In addition, the beach was about 8
minutes of walk away. So, thank you airbnb :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Equipe Fabricio Academy&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Equipe Fabricio" src="http://www.newtolife.net/images/bjj_rio/equipe_fabricio.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Equipe Fabricio Jiu Jitsu Academy is located in the street of Nossa Senhora de
Copacabana, number 1017. (See the map above) You can't really miss it, it has a
super big plastic yellow window, and there are always some kimonos hanging from
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was founded by master Fabricio Martins, a 7th dan degree coral belt of BJJ.
Fabricio Martins himself still teaches in this academy a couple of nights a
week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know Fabricio Martins personally, but on my only meeting with him he
appeared to be a really cool person. He went out of his way to shake my hand and
welcome me to his academy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found about Equipe Fabricio Jiu Jitsu academy by searching the web (As
mentioned above). It has a pretty active &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/EquipeFabricioJiuJitsu"&gt;facebook
page&lt;/a&gt; with daily pictures of
training sessions and competition days. You can also find information about it
at the &lt;a href="http://trainbjjinrio.com/fabricio-jiu-jitsu/"&gt;trainbjjinrio website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On my first day in Rio I went to the academy to find out where it is and check
the training hours. Thinking about it now, it was probably a bad idea to just
show up and not send a message to the academy ahead of time, but everything
worked just fine. Everyone was very nice and friendly (As Brazilians always are
:)). Despite my lousy Portuguese people at the academy were very patient and
explained the training hours. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Training hours" src="http://www.newtolife.net/images/bjj_rio/training_hours.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(The training hours as written by the coach)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are training sessions every morning at 7:00 at all days (Except Sunday).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At Tuesday and Thursday there is a training session at 6:00 in the morning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At Monday, Wednesday and Friday there are training sessions at 10:30, 12:00
  and 16:00.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are training sessions every night at 18:00 and 19:30 (That's where
  master Fabricio Martins sometimes shows up).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At Saturday there is an open mat training session (Mostly fights) at 10:30 in
  the morning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally, there is a training session going on at all times, except for when
people sleep or eat lunch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I remember correctly it costs about 180
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brazilian_real"&gt;reals&lt;/a&gt; to train as much as you
want for a whole month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I showed up twice a day to the training of 7:00 in the morning and to the
evening training of 18:00. The morning training session was mostly about basic
techniques (Most of them were very new to me), and it also included lots of
fights. It is usually 2 hours, sometimes a bit more. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the evening training session of 18:00 you can meet some really tough
fighters. Usually at least third of the participants were not from Brazil. I met
there people from Chile, Argentina, Jordan, Belgium and more. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Etiquette&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was never given a brochure about etiquette when training BJJ in Brazil, but I
did manage to infer some ideas from my stay in Rio, and generally from my
experience on the mat. The following advice can help you keep your friends on
the mat:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't stink. Always wash your Gi (They call it Kimono in Rio) immediately
   after you finish training. If you plan to train more than once a day, bring
   more than one Gi.  (I had three Gis with me). 
   You can really stink if you use the same Gi for a few days without washing
   it. In addition, it endangers your health and your friends health.
   In addition, make sure to wash yourself immediately after training. Somewhat
   of a trivial advice, but it could be useful if nobody ever told you about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't change your pants on the mat. There is a toilet room in every mat, and
   you should change your pants there. This one was not trivial for me. In my
   local club people don't really care where you change your pants, but then
   again, all of us are guys back home. On the other side, it seemed like
   changing your shirt on the mat is not a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be careful with new opponents. If this is your first fight with an opponent
   you don't have experience with, start easy. Even if your opponent has a very
   high belt, he might have not trained for a long time, or maybe has recovered
   from an injury. You don't know, so start easy. As the fight progresses you
   can sense if you can use more power and speed.
   Generally, don't go crazy. Remember that there is another training at the
   evening :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be on time. It seems like in Brazil being late is the usual thing. In many
   training sessions people only showed up 10 or 15 minutes after the training
   session has begun. However, I think that people will appreciate if you show
   up on time, especially if you are a guest in the academy. Being on time
   implicitly means that you appreciate other people's time, and the teacher's
   time. (It's just my opinion though. Maybe the guys there thought that there
   is something strange with me showing up on time...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Respect the teacher ('Professor' in Portuguese) of the dojo and people of
   higher rank. Even if you think you know some technique better, or you have a
   better idea about how to do something, make sure to try first what the
   teacher suggests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The BJJ training&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have only trained in Equipe Fabricio Jiu Jitsu so my experiences mostly relate
to that academy. I can only assume that training in other places in Rio are
somewhat similar, though I can't know for sure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dojo"&gt;dojo&lt;/a&gt; was made of two rooms with mats.
There were mats on the walls too, which means you can roll all the way without
being afraid of the walls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The room on the right is mostly for the younger ones, and the beginners. That
said, you can find there many tough black belts that probably want to review
their basics (Or just enjoy kicking your ass). The morning training of 07:00
every day happened there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The room on the left usually hosted more advanced training sessions. The evening
training session of 18:00 usually happened there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The 07:00-09:00 morning training session&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The training usually begins with a run around the mat, then some power
exercises. Usually a lot of abdominal exercise. Next is some crawling on the
mat. I don't know how is this called, but BJJ people have some really
interesting techniques for crawling on their backs on the mat.
The warmup part is usually about 20 minutes more or less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next comes the technique part. The coach explains some basic BJJ technique, like
getting out of mount, getting out of a
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guard_%28grappling%29"&gt;guard&lt;/a&gt;, a sweep or a basic
Judo Uchi komi (Static practice of throwing techniques, usually without actually
throwing). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally there are some fights. The coach pairs people on the mat together for
fights. This is very different from my Judo club, where you have to be somewhat
pushy to get a fight with a good opponent. Usually in every training session you
get to have something like 3-6 fights. The fights put emphasis on correct
technique, and less on great force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although many of the fights were pretty tough, my opponents always took care of
me and made sure that I stayed alive and safe, which was pretty nice. I noticed
that the higher the rank of my opponent, the smoother the fight was. The higher
belts didn't use much force at all (Yet still managed to beat me every time).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually in every morning training session there was at least one fighter with a
purple or higher belt, but in many cases there were even 2 or 3 black belt
fighters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The 18:00-19:30 evening training session&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The evening training session is instructed by a different coach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The training session begins with a warmup most of the times. (There were a few
times where the training began immediately with fights). The warmup is usually a
run around the mat, some power exercises (Mostly abdominals. Sometimes it was
400-600 reps) and some BJJ crawls on the mat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next comes the technique part. The techniques at the evening session were more
advanced than the ones at the morning sessions. During my month in Rio, the
techniques were mostly about fighting a standing person when you are on the
ground. It was a real experience watching the coach demonstrating those
techniques. He was really good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there are some fights. There are usually many people in the evening
training session, so you get to do less fights, but you do get to watch some
really good fights. In a usual training session I got to participate in about
3-4 fights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a usual evening training session almost everyone has at least a purple belt,
and sometimes you will meet even 6 or 7 black belt fighters. Many of the people
in this training session are not from Brazil, so you get to feel many different
fighting techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Main stuff that I have learned&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I showed up knowing almost nothing about BJJ, and I learned a lot during one
month of intensive training. Some of the main things I have learned and managed
to apply in my fights:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to get out of an opponent's guard, and how to do it without getting my
  hand broken.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to pass an opponent's guard from standing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some techniques for getting out of an opponent's mount.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Never give your back.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some Judo throws can put you into a trap when applied in a BJJ fight.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Comparison to Judo&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From my experience, A BJJ fight doesn't feel like a Judo fight at all. I will
list here the main differences and similarity points that I have noticed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can stand both in Judo and BJJ. In Judo, you can finish your fight with a
  throw, however in BJJ a throw will only give you a few points (and a position
  advantage), however, it won't finish the fight. You still have to come up with
  some submission to finish the fight.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing is the idea of "Pulling a guard". In BJJ it is allowed to jump
  over your opponent and catch him with the legs. In all my years of training
  Judo I have never even thought about doing this (I think that it is not
  allowed), but in BJJ this is the usual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has a very strange effect on how BJJ fighters fight. In competitions a
  BJJ fight will begin from standing. BJJ fighters usually don't stand high.
  They stand in some kind of a crouch, ready to jump over their opponent to grab
  a good position on the ground. Their crouch probably defends from a possible
  sudden guard pull of their opponent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BJJ fighters don't spend much of their time learning Judo throws (Takedowns in
  BJJ language). This is somewhat dual to the fact that many Judo fighters don't
  spend much of their time learning newaza techniques. In a competitive Judo
  fight the referee will stop the ground work pretty quickly if nothing
  interesting happens. I heard that this is about to change, but probably it
  won't change too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More things are allowed on the ground in BJJ. You can pretty much make a bar
  out of anything. Leg bars and other strange bars are allowed. The fight never
  really stops. Your opponent can be standing while your are on the ground, and
  the fight will still continue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing groundwork fights in Judo some time ago, I can recognize now many basic
mistakes I was making. In the hope that these will be useful to other Judokas
out there, I will list them here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some Judo fighters think that groundwork is just like standing, but on
  the knees. I was famous for this mistake. The two Judo fighters walk on their
  knees and try to "throw" each other on the mat. In BJJ experienced fighters
  sometimes start the fight on the opposite base: on their butt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using your back as defense. It is a common Judo groundwork technique to lay on
  your stomach and close yourself for defense. I think Judo fighters can get
  away with this just because the competition referee will usually stop the
  fight at this point. If you do this at a BJJ fight you will soon be in
  trouble. It is very hard to save yourself after you have given your back to
  your opponent. Giving your back to your opponent exposes you to all kinds of
  chokes and unfortunate things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trying to choke your opponent when you are inside his guard. Big mistake! It
  is very hard to choke someone when you are inside his guard. In addition, you
  put your arms in danger. You have to get out of the guard first. They have a
  saying in BJJ: Position before Submission. You have to get to a good position
  before you can go for the choke.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you wonder how effective is Judo groundwork in a BJJ fight, I can give you my
personal perspective. On my first days in Rio, except for a few real beginners,
everyone on the mat would beat me. On my last days there I could manage to beat
most blue belts on the mat, and have a decent fight with the purple belts. The
brown and black belts had a level of technique that was way beyond anything I
could handle :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Injuries&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally, I didn't experience any serious injury. Many fights were intense,
but it seemed like people really take care of each other. Most of the people
didn't use too much force when finishing a submission. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was told that it is a good practice to tap early, and I made sure to follow
this advice. This practice helps you focus on technique and not on using force
to escape submissions. It also lets your opponent have the experience of
applying a technique successfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On my first week of training I had some cuts on my skin in a few fingers and
toes, and also in both of my elbows. For a while it was pretty painful to sit on
my knees because of the toe cuts. I made sure to cover all my cuts with tape. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was worried that those cuts will get worse, but they somehow healed after the
first week and never appeared again. My skin in those places became a bit
tougher. I assume that those cuts happened because my skin in those places has
not yet got used to the BJJ training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used mouthguard in some of the fights, mostly at the evening training, where
fights could get tougher. I didn't use Earguards (but maybe that's because I
still lack some knowledge about life).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally I was impressed that BJJ is a sport where you can train a lot and
still stay alive if you are being reasonable with your training. I don't think I
would have been able to do Judo the same amount of time per day and stay in one
part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, I did manage to meet some people on the BJJ mat that were taking it
easy because of injuries they have. It's a martial art, after all, and injuries
are probably inevitable part of the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Competitions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went to see one BJJ competition during my month in Rio (I didn't participate,
though). It was a great experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The competition was divided over a few days, where each day was dedicated for
different sets of belts and weight classes. I went to see the black belts
competition day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outside the competition stadium there were some stands that sold cold
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A%C3%A7a%C3%AD_palm"&gt;Açaí&lt;/a&gt; and BJJ Kimonos. The
entry was free for observers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were about different mats with fights happening simultaneously. The mats
were inside a big cage, most likely to stop the crazy crowd from stepping into
the fights. Every fighter came with his whole team, and the team members made
sure to support their fighters very loudly :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fights were very technical but still involved lots of speed and power. For
most of the fights I understood very little of what I saw, but I could still
appreciate the quality of the fights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole event had a great vibe to it. Highly recommended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="BJJ Competition" src="http://www.newtolife.net/images/bjj_rio/bjj_competition.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(A Brazilian Jiu Jitsu Competition)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Portuguese language&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Portuguese is the official language in Brazil. People in Brazil can sometimes
understand some really basic English or Spanish, but don't count on it. That
said, Brazilians (And Rio's &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carioca"&gt;Cariocas&lt;/a&gt;
especially) are generally very friendly people and they will try to help you
even if you don't speak a word in Portuguese.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I brought with me
&lt;a href="http://www.pimsleur.com/learn-portuguese-brazilian/"&gt;Pimsleur&lt;/a&gt; Brazilian
Portuguese audio course together with an old MP3 player, and learned a bit every
day. It really helped. If you know some English or Spanish, you can catch up the
basics of Portuguese pretty quickly. My language is written from right to left.
If I managed to learn some Portuguese you have no excuses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing even a little Portuguese can really help you with the daily logistics
and also on the BJJ training sessions. On the very least, it shows people that
you made some effort, so they can make their effort to meet you halfway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Safety&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I told some of my friends that I am going to visit Brazil, I was
immediately warned that Brazil could be a dangerous place. I have to admit that
during my 2 months in Brazil nothing bad happened to me. On the contrary: The
Brazilian people were very friendly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that if you follow some general reasonable safety guidelines nothing
bad should happen to you (At least not too often).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are my main conclusions regarding safety in Rio, and generally in Brazil.
I got most of these pieces of advice from locals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the people in Brazil are extremely friendly and helpful. Like in any
  other place in the world, there is a very small minority of people that might
  be dangerous for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Never walk with too much money in wallet. Have about enough for the day. If
  somebody ever tries to rob you, just give him the wallet. Don't fight for 100
  reals, your life doesn't worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't put all your money in one pocket. Split it between 2 or more, so that if
  you get robbed, you can still recover and buy a metro ticket back home.
  Another idea is to have two wallets. I usually walk with two wallets when I
  visit far places in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't take your passport with you. Leave your passport at home / hostel /
  hotel, and take a copy with you instead. During my stay in Brazil I was only
  asked for my passport when moving to another major destination: In long term
  buses or Flights. You don't need your passport on the street.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't wear shiny valuables. I did see some of the locals wear valuables,
  so this might be an outdated advice, but still: If something is important to
  you, don't bring it to the street.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't walk with a big backpackers bag at the streets. A small simple backpack
  is ok.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Walk with comfortable shoes. Heels are not made to survive Rio's streets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beware of ATM scams. (Especially in GIG airport) Before you head to Brazil
  tell your credit card company that you are going to do so. If you can, come
  with two different international credit cards. 
  Be alert when you go to withdraw cash from ATMs. Use only ATMs inside banks,
  prefer the ones that have a guard. Look closely at the ATM and make sure that
  it looks reasonable. Try to move the plastic where you enter your card, to
  make sure nothing was installed there. Cover the keypad with your other hand
  when you type in your PIN, to make sure it is not filmed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't walk to strange places at night. Some places should not be visited even
  during the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Food&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rio de Janeiro is a place that understands the needs of the BJJ fighter. You can
find quality healthy food at reasonable prices. I don't eat meat so I can not
share a first-hand experience of trying it, but people say that the meat in
Brazil is pretty good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mostly ate at &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buffet"&gt;Kilo Restaurants&lt;/a&gt;. Those
are restaurants where you choose whatever you want and you pay by the weight. I
ate very often at &lt;a href="http://www.temperarte.com.br/"&gt;Restaurante Temperarte&lt;/a&gt; in Rua
Bolivar, where a big meal should cost about 40 reals. (It depends of course, on
how much you eat). Most likely you can find a 30 reals big meal in a less fancy
Kilo restaurant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Food at Restaurante Temperarte" src="http://www.newtolife.net/images/bjj_rio/temperarte.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Food at Restaurante Temperarte)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another great feature of the Brazilian food are the fruit shakes, that are
virtually everywhere. There is a fruit shake stand every 300 meters or so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really liked the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A%C3%A7a%C3%AD_palm"&gt;Açaí&lt;/a&gt;. I
think that I ate at least half a kilo of Açaí every day. You can get half a kilo
for about 10-15 reals. When I came back home I tried to buy some frozen Açaí and
make it with my own blender, but whatever I tried, it was never as good as the
Açaí I ate in Rio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there are the supermarkets. There are pretty big supermarkets in Rio.
If you have a kitchen, you can buy some groceries and make your own food. It's
probably the cheapest option for food in Rio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Gear&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't have much experience with BJJ gear, but I was told you shouldn't expect
any great bargains for BJJ gear in Brazil. If you have stuff that you need on
the mat, you should probably bring it with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I write here the list of stuff I brought (That is related to BJJ training). It
might be different for you, but at least it could give you some ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two Gis. I brought two white Judo Gis, and bought a black BJJ Kimono at Equipe
  Fabricio's Academy. (About 350 reals) I learned why BJJ people love black so
  much: If your Gi is white, it will turn black after a while anyways from all
  the time spent on the mat. 
  I think that three Gis is a good number if you want to train twice a day and
  show up with a clean dry Gi every time. You can do with less, but then you
  might show up with a dry dirty Gi or a clean wet Gi. (It's somewhat of a
  philosophical question what is worse).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knee and elbow protectors. I think that I have used one of the elbow
  protectors for one training session, but that's all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tiger_Balm"&gt;Tiger balm&lt;/a&gt;. I used it about once
  for my shoulder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.traumeel.com/"&gt;Traumeel ointment&lt;/a&gt;. It saved me once at home, so I
  took it with me to Rio. I used it a few times in the first week for an
  inflammation on my elbow, which happened because of an old Judo injury (Lots
  of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seoi_nage"&gt;Seoi Nage&lt;/a&gt;). The inflammation was
  gone, though I'm not sure if it's the ointment that made it happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tape. Quality sport tape is hard to find where I live, so I assumed it might
  be rare in other parts of the world too. I brought two rolls. I didn't use
  much of the tape I brought, just a bit on the first two weeks. I don't know if
  you can find good sport tape in Rio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="My Gis, drying" src="http://www.newtolife.net/images/bjj_rio/gis_drying.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(My Gis, drying)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was planning to travel Brazil after my first month in Rio, so after my last
training session I washed my clothes, packed everything into a box and sent it
by mail back home. Gis can be pretty heavy and I didn't want them on my back for
another month. It cost about 400 reals to send the three Gis (And some other
stuff) back home. The package arrived after about one month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Gis Package" src="http://www.newtolife.net/images/bjj_rio/package.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(This package has arrived after about one month)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Stuff to do in Rio de Janeiro&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rio de Janeiro is a great city. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things I liked the most about Rio is the people: The
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carioca"&gt;Cariocas&lt;/a&gt;. Most people in Rio are very
warm and expressive. I lost my way more than once in Rio and people went out of
their way to help me, despite my poor Portuguese. The people in Rio generally
seem to be pretty happy and easy going. Nobody is in a hurry. Everyone is a bit
late, but nobody is really worried about it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost everyone walk in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Havaianas"&gt;Havaianas&lt;/a&gt;
with a great skill, even on the rough street floors (I tried to do it myself,
but I think I was not born with the required skill). During the day you can see
many people with their swimsuit on, and it seems like there are always people
at the beach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a high awareness for health and sport, or at least this is what it
feels like. There are many shops for healthy food, and many people on the
street look very fit. There are trails near the beach for runners and bike
riders, and people are using them during all the times of the day. It is also
pretty hard to ignore all the martial art academies signs on the streets, and
the street commercials for UFC fights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I collected here some of the places I enjoyed visiting in Rio:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beach. Rio is famous for its beaches, and rightly so. I visited the beach
  of Copacabana and the beach of Ipanema. Both are really nice. You can get a
  chair for the whole day for about 5 reals. The sun is good and the people
  are beautiful. Don't miss it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Corcovado mountain, and the statue of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christ_the_Redeemer_%28statue%29"&gt;Christ the
  Redeemer&lt;/a&gt;
  (Cristo Redentor in portuguese). It's a pretty high mountain that has the
  statue of Jesus with his hands to the sides. The statue itself is pretty big.
  There is a train that takes you to the top of the mountain, and you can see
  all of Rio from above. On the way up you can buy small status of Jesus that
  glow in the dark. At the top you can also see many tourists that try to take
  a selfie picture with Jesus Christ. If only Jesus had known...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sugarloaf_Mountain"&gt;Sugarloaf mountain&lt;/a&gt; is
  another very high mountain next to sea. You get to see a beautiful view of
  Rio and to buy Açaí at the top. I have also seen some small monkeys at the
  top.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.feirahippieipanema.com/"&gt;Hippie fair&lt;/a&gt; in Rio. It is open
  every Sunday. This is a pretty large market that is made of many booths. You
  can buy there all kinds of Brazilian souvenirs, jewelery and art. Above all I
  recommend the cakes sold on each of four sides of the market square. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nossa Senhora de Copacabana street. This street is one of my favourites in
  Rio. It is a pretty long street, and it is pretty crowded most of the day.
  You can see there many people in swimsuits walking to the see, many shops and
  restaurants, and various booths that sell stuff. Equipe Fabricio Jiu Jitsu
  Academy is on this street too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.museunacional.ufrj.br/"&gt;Rio's National Museum&lt;/a&gt; and the park
  around it. When I visited there they had some dinosaur skeletons and some
  mummies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Transportation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mostly used the metro lines when travelling around. The metro doesn't cover a
big part of Rio, but it does reach some interesting places. You can buy a metro
ticket for about 3.5 reals for the whole day. If you use it a lot, consider
getting a metro card and load it ahead of time. I don't think you get any
discount for doing that, but it will save you the hassle of waiting at the
line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For anywhere that the metro doesn't reach, I took a taxi. Taxis in Rio are not
so expensive. I remember one taxi ride that took about 30 minutes, and I ended
up paying about 30 reals. Taxis in Rio use a counter to determine the final
price of the drive, so make sure your driver uses a counter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you plan on using a taxi, I recommend checking out the
&lt;a href="http://www.99taxis.com/en/"&gt;99taxis&lt;/a&gt; mobile app. It can help you connect with
reliable taxi drivers. If you don't have internet connection, in most places it
should not be too difficult to hail a taxi from the street. Before you get in,
make sure that the driver has a counter and a taxi license. The Taxi license
should be somewhere on the front, with his picture on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven't tried the buses, so I don't have much to say about them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Money&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Costs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The currency used in Brazil is
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brazilian_real"&gt;real&lt;/a&gt;. I think that Brazil is a
bit more expensive to live in than most of its Spanish speaking neighbours. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are my estimated costs if you plan on staying in Rio for BJJ training for
one month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flight: Check how much it costs to fly to Rio from your country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accommodation: About $1000 - $1500 (US dollars) if you use airbnb to rent an
    apartment. You can find a cheaper apartment if you manage to rent directly
    from someone in Rio, but it will take you some more logistics. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Food: About 70-100 reals a day. It depends how much you eat out (And
    where). If you make all your food yourself, it will probably be even
    cheaper. Remember that if you train every day, you have to eat well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BJJ training: About 180 reals for a month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simple math will give you a maximum cost of $2300 US dollars per month, without
the flight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Managing your money&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding managing your money in Rio: I mentioned in the safety part some
safety tips about your money and ATMs. In addition, you should know that
getting money out of ATMs in Rio could sometimes be a hard task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My advice to you: Show up with two different international credit cards. I came
with a Visa and a Mastercard. This is useful because if one of your cards does
not work with some bank, your other card might work. Also, in case one of your
credit cards will be cancelled by the credit card company (Due to some credit
card fraud).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I managed to withdraw money from the following banks: Itaú, Santander and
Bradesco. (All of them are somewhat red or orange). I never managed to withdraw
money from any other bank. You might have a different experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also be aware that the money runs out in most of the ATMs in Sunday, so be sure
to withdraw enough money to survive the weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every withdraw from the ATMs has costed me some constant commission, so in
every withdraw I took the maximum amount of money possible (800 reals).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I always paid with cash, but it seemed like the locals pay with credit card
even for pretty cheap things, like a small meal at a cafe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Final Notes&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Training BJJ in Rio was one of my best martial art experiences ever. I learned
a lot during this month and I already miss the people in Equipe Fabricio Jiu
Jitsu Academy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are not sure if it worth it, then let me tell you, it does. Buy the
flight ticket and start rolling on the mat.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>2 months of training at the Kodokan</title><link href="http://www.newtolife.net/2-months-of-training-at-the-kodokan.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-08-30T12:13:00+02:00</updated><author><name>newtolife</name></author><id>tag:www.newtolife.net,2014-08-30:2-months-of-training-at-the-kodokan.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A sign with the Judo spirits in Japanese" src="http://www.newtolife.net/images/kodokan/judo_spirits.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(A sign at the Kodokan Hostel)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Intro&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the months 5-6/2014 I stayed at the Kodokan for the purpose of Judo
training. Getting to the Kodokan was kind of a bet for me. Before getting there,
I really didn't know anything about how it is going to be like. There is not
much information (At least not in English), about what the Kodokan really is,
what should one bring and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article is a summary of what I have learned about living and training at
the Kodokan. It can help you understand what it is all about, and also decide if
you want to get there yourself. In such a case, you will also find here some
information about how to prepare yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some words about myself: I am practicing Judo since the year 1991. At the time
of writing I have a blue belt. I have some experience with participating in Judo
competitions in my home country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to remind you that this is not an official document about the Kodokan. It
mostly reflects my experience (And opinions) from my last stay there, so
inacurracies might show up here and there. If you are going to rely on
something written here, make sure to double check it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can contact me by email at thenewtolife(&amp;amp;)outlook.com.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Some history&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kodokan"&gt;Kodokan&lt;/a&gt; is the Headquarters of the
Judo martial art around the world. It was founded by Kano Jigoro in 1882, for
the purpose of Judo practice. Since its founding it moved a few times, and these
days it can be found in Bunkyo, Tokyo (Japan), near the Kasuga station.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Building Structure&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Kodokan is an 8 levels building (Plus a basement floor). 
A visual description could be found
&lt;a href="http://www.newtolife.net/docs/kodokan_quick_guide.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first floor is where you will usually enter the building from. This is also
where the souvenir shop is located. At the shop You can find some books about
Judo, Kodokan belts, and many Judo souvenirs that you may buy. You can also get
there training tape, which is very convenient. From the first floor you can get
to the elevators to other floors in the building, or use the stairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the second floor there is a Museum and a Library. It is open in Monday-Friday
to the general public. I have been to the Museum myself. It is pretty small, but
very exciting to see, at least in my opinion. It explains a bit about the
history of Judo, and shows old items that relate to the founding of Judo. There
is also a Library in that floor, where you can read books or watch videos. You
can't borrow the books - You can only read them inside the library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example - a friend of mine was preparing to his
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dan_%28rank%29"&gt;Shodan&lt;/a&gt; (Black belt) test at the
Kodokan, so he was watching a video of &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nage-no-kata"&gt;Nage No
Kata&lt;/a&gt; at the library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third floor is the Kodokan hostel. Basically it means that there are a
few rooms around there (Dormitories and private rooms). Those rooms are
designated for Judokas that come to practice Judo at the Kodokan. It also
contains toilets, showers and washing machines. I will expand on the Kodokan
hostel later in this article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 4th floor is the Dojo entrance. (Dojo is the place where you actually
practice Judo). The Dojo is not there - there are a few mats in the 5th - 7th
floors. The 4th floor contains the reception (Where you have to show your card
before getting to the Dojo), and also dressing rooms. The dressing rooms at that
floor are mostly for Judokas that don't live inside the Kodokan hostel. They
contain lockers where you can put your things (The lockers work without a key -
They are combination lockers, so you don't have to worry about keeping the key
during training). I think that the dressing rooms also contain showers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 5th - 7th floors are were the Dojos are. The 5th and 6th floors contain a
few rooms with mats. The 7th floor contains the biggest mat - This is were the
black belts practice randori. Note that you can get to the 5th-7th floors only
using the stairs from the 4th floor. This is to make sure that you go through
the reception at the 4th floor before getting inside the dojo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 8th floor is the spectator seating floor. You can get there directly with
the elevator. (You can also use the stairs, but that is a long journey). From
the 8th floor you can see the the mat of the 7th floor. (However you can not see
the 6th and 5th floors). On normal training days, Sometimes tourists show up at
that floor to take pictures. This floor is also very crowded with spectators
during competition days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The 8th and 7th floor during a competition day at the
Kodokan" src="http://www.newtolife.net/images/kodokan/kodokan_competition.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(The 8th and 7th floor during a competition day at the Kodokan)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also the roof to mention. The roof is not an official part of the
building, however it can have some important uses. You can leave you Judogi
there to dry. I have also seen some people doing Uchikomi practice up there, in
days where there was no training at the Kodokan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ground floor (Also known as B1 floor) contains the security office, a
Kitchen and a Gym. There is also a cafeteria down there, however it seems to be
a place for special events. It also seems to be a bit expensive compared to
other options that you have on the street. During my stay in the Kodokan I have
never seen any Judokas eating there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The security office is responsible for the security (Of course), but also for
other things, like handing you the key for the Gym, closing and opening the
showers at different times of the day, assigning people to beds at the Kodokan
hostel and so on. More on that later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another part of the Kodokan to mention is the International Department. It is
not part of the 8 floors building I have just discussed. Looking from outside
the building - The 8 floors building is followed by a Do It Yourself shop, which
is then followed by an office building. The International Department is at the
ground floor of the office building. Between the 8 floors building and the
International department you can also see the statue of Kano. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The Statue of Kano, outside the Kodokan
building" src="http://www.newtolife.net/images/kodokan/kano_statue.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(The statue of Kano Jigoro, outside the Kodokan building)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The International Department is the place where you sign up for accomodation and
training at the Kodokan. If you plan to visit the Kodokan, the International
Department is your first stop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Judo training&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are a Judoka, you probably really care about how is the training at the
Kodokan. I'm sorry for the Fluff before, but you had to know it to understand
this section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Courses&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few &lt;a href="http://www.newtolife.net/docs/general_info.pdf"&gt;different courses&lt;/a&gt; you can
take at the Kodokan. I mostly participated in the Randori session myself, so I
know little of the other courses, but I have some speculations from what I have
seen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will begin with the Randori session. If you are an experienced Judoko (Black
belt, or you have been training many years), you will most likely want to
participate at the Randori session. The Randori session happens almost every
day. (1800-2000 Mon-Fri and 1800-1930 Sat.) on the 7th floor Dojo. The Randori
session is not really a course. It is more of a free sparring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After introduction to the rules and ettiquite of the Dojo, you will be pretty
much on your own. You do your own warmup, you can do some Uchikomi with other
judokas on the mat, and then you can do some randori with the judokas on the
mat. There is no coach, or any strict frame to the randori session. If you are
used to having a coach back home it might take you some time to get used to it
:)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other courses are more framed, and you get to have a coach. There is a class
for younger boys and girls, classes for women and also classes for beginners.
Some of those classes are on different dojos. I know little of those courses and
I recommend that if you consider checking them out, you should contact the
International Department by email first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other classes (Beginners, Women, boys and girls) sometimes show up at the
7th floor. By what I have seen, it seems like the classes have a very strict
frame, and the judokas there have great technique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing to mention is the Kata lessons. During my stay at the Kodokan
there was a series of Kata lessons (Every Tuesday, 1700-1900. You may continue
to the Randori from 1900 to 2000 right after it). In those lessons there were a
few senseis, and you could ask them about how to do different Katas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I participated in a few of those Kata lessons. The senseis taught me the
real basics (How to do proper Ukemi and basic Judo rolls), and also Nage No
Kata. I have also seen there a few judokas practicing more advanced Katas. (They
had models of knifes and guns, and they were shouting from time to time).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the above, there are special courses that take place on a
specific time of the year. Information about those courses and their specific
dates could be found on the Kodokan website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Training Costs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Registration fee is 8000 JPY. (You pay it only once in a lifetime).
The randori session costs 5000 JPY for a month, or 800 JPY per day. If you pay
monthly, you should get a card, which costs 500 JPY to produce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The card that you get can be recharged at the 4th floor (At the reception), to
get you more days of training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically after setting up the registration free and the card, if you pay
monthly, a training day at the Kodokan will cost you about 5000/30 ~ 166 JPY,
which is pretty cheap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Dojo ettiquite&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a westerner, you might not understand why would I mention these kind of
subjects here, however in Japan and generally in places in the east, ettiquite
could be very important. This is especially relevant to the Dojo. I cover here
the real basics. You can also find those in the &lt;a href="http://www.newtolife.net/docs/etiquette_eng.pdf"&gt;dojo
ettiquite&lt;/a&gt; document from the Kodokan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should show up at the dojo with a white Judogi (Only white. Other colors
like blue are not allowed. If you are a guy, you can't wear anything beneath
your Judogi). You have to make sure that your Judogi is clean and smells good.
Also make sure that you are clean and smell good. Japanese people could be very
indirect, and if you are not clean or smell bad, they might not want to
practice with you, without clarifying the real reason for that. In addition,
keep your nails cut. This is for your own safety and your opponent safety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever you enter the mat, you have to perform a standing bow to the mat. You
should also perform a standing bow to the mat whenever you leave the mat. In
some training sessions you should also bow to the picture of Kano (In every
dojo at the kodokan there is a picture of Kano on one of the walls). If you are
not sure, just look at what the sensei does. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before practicing with another judoka, you should bow to the other judoka (A
Sitting bow). The direction of the bow is also important - You and the other
judoka should form together a line which is parallel to the wall where the
picture of Kano resides. This is to make sure none of you has his back to the
picture of Kano. In addition, the higher ranked judoka should be on the right,
and the lower ranked judoka should be on the left. (This rule is important to
remember when you practice with higher ranked judokas).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some other basic rules that I mention here just in case: You can't run around
the mat. (In some Dojos in the world this is done as warmup. However in the
Kodokan you are not allowed to do that). You can't play with your belt, take
off your jacket, or leave your jacket open. If you want to rearrange your belt
or jacket, you should do that in &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seiza"&gt;seiza&lt;/a&gt;
(The Judo sitting - on your knees). If you are resting, you can't just lie on
the mat. You should sit in seiza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the rules here might be overwhelming if you see it for the first time, but
don't worry, you get used to it after a few randori sessions. People will help
you out if you don't remember anything, and will be forgiving if you did
something wrong :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Judo&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main property of the Kodokan Judo (At least by what I have seen) is the
emphasis on accurate technique. It is less about power and speed.
(Although the seeker of power and speed will find them on the Kodokan, too).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing to know about the Kodokan Judo is that it has different rules
compared to the european and international competitions. For example - You may
grab the legs of you opponent. This is not legal according to the international
rules, however at the Kodokan you will see judokas grabbing the legs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the main dojo (Randori session) you may invite other judokas to uchikomi or
randori (Also ne-waza fights are possible). The amount of judokas on the main
dojo varies from day to day. There could be very crowded days from time to
time. (Wednesday is the university teams day, and it is a very crowded day).
Generally speaking, you find at least 50 people on the mat, from which you can
do randori with at least 10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;randori with another judoka is not bounded in time, and can last as long as you
want (or can). Some randori sessions last even more than 20 or 30 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About the use of power - Many Judokas that show up at the Kodokan for the first
time are very excited to fight, and they use lots of power. I admit that it
happened to me to. On my first week at the Kodokan, I participated in many
randori sessions and used as much power as possible. In the beginning, I
couldn't understand why other judokas on the mat use so little power. I thought
they go easy on me. It took me about one week to get a better understanding of
how it works. Let me try to explain it here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few reasons not to exagerate in the use of power in your fights.
The first one is that excessive use of power might cause injuries. (Both as a
sudden trauma, or from continuos use of your muscles). In the end of my first
week at the Kodokan, it was hard for me to lift my hands to open doors at the
building because of the excessive training and use of power. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second reason to use less power, is that the power might mask the
technique. Use of power will work against an opponent of the same weight, but
it will not work against heavier opponents. In the case of heavier opponents,
you will have to rely on your technique. If your main strategy in fight is
relying on your power, you will not be able to win fights against heavier
opponents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding the importance of winning - At my home dojo, people are very eager to
win, and therefore they do everything to avoid falling on their backs. It is
not the same in the Kodokan. As a general rule at the Kodokan, if your opponent
demonstrate perfect technique, you will not try to resist the throw. You will
just fall. It was hard for me to adjust to this idea in the beginning. It took
me a few weeks to be able to fall down for a good technique, and not try to
resist using power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my opinion there is much behind this idea of letting go when your opponent
throws correctly. It allows you to avoid many injuries, and it also helps your
opponent to get the feeling of throwing and getting an ippon. If your opponent
is less experienced, it will help him gain experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can get much help and advice from experienced judokas on the mat. There is
nothing really formal about it, you just have to spot them and ask them. One
way to do it is ask for randori, and then in the end of the randori session you
will be able to ask them questions about one technique or another. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Different judokas on the mat specialize in different techniques. Many judokas
at the Kodokan are very good with the legs. They have great Uchi Mata and other
similar leg techniques. It seems that even the beginners at the beginners class
perform very good Uchi Mata. At the same time, you will find judokas the
specialize in other techniques, like Seoi Nage and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some more senior judokas specialize in Ne-Waza techniques. This might be
because at their age it is harder to participate in standing randori. If you
want to learn some Ne-Waza, a good idea would be to spot one of the senior
judokas sitting on the mat and ask him for a Ne-Waza fight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are looking for a tough fight, every week, at least for one day (Usually
Wednesday), the university teams show up at the Kodokan. The university
students are usually young (But experienced) judokas, usually 18-21 in age, and
they are very strong. You are allowed to ask them for a fight. If you talk to
the right people, you might be able to practice at one of the university dojos.
I heard that it is a great experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Competitions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few competitions at the Kodokan that occur regularly. The first one
is the Tsukinami Shiai, which happens every month. I didn't manage to
participate in this competition, as it is probably only for Japanese people.
From what I heard, in this competition Japanese judokas at the Kodokan can earn
points on their way to the Shodan (Black belt) test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another competition is the famous Red and White contest. It is a very old
contest (Since 1884!) In this competition the judokas are separated into two
teams - Red and White. The rules are as follows: The first two judoka from the
two teams fight. The winner of the fight stays, and the judoka who lost the
fight is replaced by the next member of his team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the interesting parts of this contest is that very light judokas may
find themselves fighting very heavy judokas, as there are no weight classes.
There is a class though for judokas with a rank lower than a Shodan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was also told that judokas which manage to score a few consecutive ippons in
this contest are awarded the next judo rank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Judo competition at the Kodokan" src="http://www.newtolife.net/images/kodokan/kodokan_competition_2.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(A competition at the Kodokan)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Exams&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as I understand, the Kodokan Judo ranks are as follows: One begins from
a white belt, and then he could accuire a few Kyu ranks. Even after having a
few Kyu ranks, the judoka still has a white belt. (Japanese judokas at the
Kodokan have only two belts: white and black. As a result you will sometimes
meet white belt Judoka that fight very well).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a Judoka is ready, he is tested for Shodan (Black belt), which is really
the first dan, or the "entry dan". There are 10 different dans. In the Kodokan it
is very usual to meet 3rd dan holders, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is possible to take dan exams at the Kodokan. The procedure seems to be a
bit different for Japanese judokas and foreigners. As a foreigner, you have the
following possibilities: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a Shodan from your home country, you can do the exam for Shodan at
the Kodokan, and then you are allowed to move to the next dans at the Kodokan.
If you don't yet have a Shodan from your home country, you will be able to take
the Shodan exam at the Kodokan, however you will not be eligible for Shodan
until you get a certification from your own country. Maybe there could be
special cases that go around the rules, but as a general practice, it seems like
if you don't have Shodan from your home dojo, you will not have a Shodan from
the Kodokan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An exam for Shodan could contain for example - Demonstration of ukemi and Judo
rolls, Questions about a few random techniques, and &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nage-no-kata"&gt;Nage No
Kata&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Kodokan Hostel&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Document about the Kodokan hostel rules could be found
&lt;a href="http://www.newtolife.net/docs/kodokan_hostel_rules.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Kodokan hostel is at the 3rd floor. It is not really a hostel in the
traveller's sense. It's basically a floor with a lobby, a few rooms, toilets
and showers. The floor is separated to two parts - One for women and one for
men. There are also separate showers and toilets for women and men.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Kodokan hostel offers different kinds of accomodation. There are the dorms,
and there are also single and twin rooms. The cost for the dormitory is 1800
JPY per night. Single room without bath is 3500 JPY per night, Single room with
bath is 5000 JPY and twin room with bath is 9000 JPY. I heard that there is
also a tatame room somewhere, but I have never seen it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared to other parts of the world this accomodation is pretty expensive,
however I don't think you can find in Tokyo accomodation which is cheaper than
the Kodokan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I slept at the dormitories, so this is the only type of accomodation I can talk
about here. The dormitories contain 20 beds (10 bunk beds). Each bed includes a
curtain around it, so that one could get some privacy. The curtain is also very
useful to obtain some darkness, if you want to sleep while the main light is
on. Next to each bunk bed there are two electric sockets. In addition, every
bed has a personal lamp. Between the beds there are wires that are used to hang
clothes. (Mostly Judogis)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the front of the room (Next to the door) there are lockers. These lockers
are combination lockers. You pick a secret number and lock the locker - no key
is needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dormitories don't have any windows, but they have a strong air conditioner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The Kodokan Hostel's dormitories" src="http://www.newtolife.net/images/kodokan/kodokan_dorms.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(The Kodokan Hostel's dormitories)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Down the hallway there are the shower room and the toilet. The shower room is
closed most of the time. It is open in specific times of the day, usually right
after the randori session. When the Kodokan hostel is crowded, the shower room
is open more often. The shower room contains japanese style showers (They are
somehow low, with a low mirror), and two small pools. One is usually filled
with hot water, and the other one with cold water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The toilet room contain western style toilets, and also one asian style toilet.
There are two coin operated washing machine at the toilet room. If I remember
correctly, using the washing machine costs 200 JPY. Note that there are no
dryers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Kodokan hostel's washing machines" src="http://www.newtolife.net/images/kodokan/washing_machines.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(The Kodokan Hostel's washing machines, at the males' toilets room)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lobby contains a few couches, a small television screen (It is mostly used
to watch Sumo contests), and a cupboard with books. There are also a few
vending machine for drinks, and a vending machine for noodles with hot water.
There is also free wifi around the lobby (It is harder to catch from inside the
dormitory, but it is possible if done correctly).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The Kodokan Hostel lobby" src="http://www.newtolife.net/images/kodokan/kodokan_hostel_lobby.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(The Kodokan Hostel Lobby)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guests of the Kodokan hostel may also use the Gym or the Kitchen. The Gym and
the Kitchen are at the basement floor (B1 floor), and may be used upon request
from the security office. Usage of the Gym requires at least two people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not very experienced with gyms, so I present here the opinion of my
friends from the Kodokan. They said that the gym is a bit old fashioned and
basic, but it contains everything that you may need. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same goes for the kitchen. It looks a bit old, but it contains most of the
things that you might need: A stove, a fridge, rice machine and lots of cooking
pots. If you ever get there, know that the knifes are under the sink. It took
us a month to find it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The Kodokan Kitchen" src="http://www.newtolife.net/images/kodokan/kodokan_kitchen.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(The Kodokan Kitchen)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the facilities of the Kodokan hostel are cleaned daily (Sometimes even more
than once a day).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Kodokan hostel has curfew. At 22:00 the main entrance door is locked (There
is a back door to the basement though), and at 00:00 the whole Kodokan is
locked. You can not get in or out after 00:00. The Kodokan opens again at about
5:30.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Daily life experience&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The dorms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I stayed about two months at the dormitories. The dorms are not for the faint
of heart. It was not always easy, however staying there was a major part of the
experience. I had the chance to meet talented judokas from all over the world,
and really get to know them, because we slept at the same room, going through
the same things every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have met both teams of judokas, and also people that came alone to the
Kodokan, like me. Big teams of judokas were usually given a separate dormitory
room, however small teams or single judokas were assigned to the dormitory were
I stayed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dorm room is filled with graffiti of previous judokas who stayed at the
kodokan. Interestingly enough, they always write down their name and their
weight class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the lobby there are usually a few people calling home, chatting or watching
something on the TV (As noted before, it is often Sumo).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The language and culture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This document will not be complete without dealing with the Japanese language.
You might be wondering if it is possible to survive the Kodokan and generally -
Tokyo, without knowing Japanese. From my experience, you will get into
difficulties from time to time, but you will manage to make it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the Kodokan, the people at the International Department are able to speak
some English. In addition, you will always find on the mat some sensei, or
someone, that knows some English. The security guys at the Kodokan also know
some English.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the Japanese people you will meet, however, will not be able to speak
English. They know as much English as you know Japanese. You can make life much
easier for you and for them if you take the first step, and learn a few Japanese
expressions yourself. The crucial ones, at least in my opinion, are
"Konnichiwa" (Good afternoon), "Sumimasen" (Sorry), "Arigatou gozaimasu"
(Formal Thank you). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides knowing the language, another very important thing in Japan is the
politeness. If you are a westerner, this might be new to you. There is the idea
of "face" in the east. Let me demonstrate it with a few examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I walked once in Tokyo and I saw a homeless guy on the street, drinking from
cans people threw to the recycling bin. I bought a bottle of green tea from a
store near by, and gave it to him. Surprisingly, he shouted angrily at me in
Japanese. Only later I was explained that by trying to help him on the street,
I caused him to lose his "face". I embarassed him in public, and this is why he
was angry at me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another example - If you ask something, and somebody wants to answer "no" to
you, he will usually not do it directly, so you will not lose your "face". He
will just state some indirect reason why something is difficult to do, or not
possible. Many times when you notice people have long explanations about things
in Japan, you should know that they actually mean "no", in a polite way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding Hygiene - I was travelling to a few places in the world, and I have
never seen a place cleaner than Japan. You should know that if something looks
clean, and you used it, you are expected to leave it about as clean as it was.
In addition, you are expected to carry your own garbage - It is pretty rare
to find garbage bins on the street.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another concept is shoes ettiquite - Some places are considered to be cleaner
than others, and in order to avoid mixing the clean with the unclean, you will
be requested to remove your shoes, or change them into slippers. As an example,
sometimes when you walk into a toilet, you should change your shoes into
slippers provided inside the toilet room. When you leave, you should remove the
slippers and change back to your shows. Also, if you walk into somebody's house
(or even a store, sometimes) you will have to change your shoes into slippers
provided by the host.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though there are many ettiquite rules, you shouldn't worry. You don't have
to remember everything. Walking around Tokyo, knowing even just a few Japanese
expressions can take you a long way. If you show that you made the effort, and
you talk politely, Japanese people will go out of their way to help you out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Food&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Food is a major topic if you are going to practice every day. I write here my
main conclusions regarding dealing with food around the Kodokan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First there is the possibility of eating out. Outside the Kodokan (On Hakusan
Dori) you can find many good restaurants, which are not very expensive. I don't
name there here because those kind of things do change with time. The good
places close usually a bit before 21:00, so you should hurry if you just finish
the randori session at 20:00.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't eat meat or chicken, but I still had lots of possibilities. I ate
mostly noodles (Udon or Soba), rice, fish, eggs and tofu. All of those were
really in a walking distance from the Kodokan, on Hakusan Dori. A basic dish
usually costs 690 JPY, and can go up to 900 JPY if you decide to be fancy. From
my experience you will need about 4 such meals per day (or more) to survive a
training day at the Kodokan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Udon and Tuna" src="http://www.newtolife.net/images/kodokan/udon_and_tuna.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(A dish of Udon and Tuna at OOO restaurant, Hakusan Dori)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Salmon and Avocado" src="http://www.newtolife.net/images/kodokan/salmon_and_avocado.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(A dish of Salmon and Avocado, Hakusan Dori, Tokyo Dome)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also the convenience stores (Seven eleven, Lawson, Family mart). They
are really everywhere, and they are open 24 hours a day. If you are hungry in
the middle of the night somewhere in Tokyo, those stores will save you. You can
get there lots of snacks, and also some solid food (Like rice balls with salmon
or tuna, for example. about 100-150 JPY for a riceball). If you are going to
practice every day, though, I will not recommend basing your diet on the
contents of those stores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are on a budget, there is the possibility of buying groceries and
cooking them yourself in the Kodokan kitchen. It takes a bit more time to eat
that way, and a bit of a hassle (You have to request the key from the security
guy), but it is much cheaper, and you also get the control to what gets into
your mouth. You can buy some of the groceries at the convinience stores, but
you can also buy them for a cheaper price at specialized supermarkets. You will
just have to walk a bit more. (I think on my last days in Tokyo I have noticed
that a new Don Quixote store is being built in front of the Kodokan, so might
be able to get things in there).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ate part of my meals at the kitchen. Mostly things like Pasta, eggs and rice
in different combinations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far we have covered proteins and carbs. To get vitamins could be a bit more
challenging in Tokyo, as fruits and vegetables are very expensive and not very
common. Fruits and vegetables could be bought in convenience stores or in
specialized supermarkets. I remember that a banana would cost something like
100-150 JPY, an Apple might cost something like 200-300 JPY and a cucumber
might cost something like 30-60 JPY. Avocados could be traded for gold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another option might be buy multivitamin products. They are very common around
the convenience stores, and show up in many forms. However, I have no idea if
those things really work, so do it at your own risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Dealing with Money&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Tokyo most of the stores and businesses take only cash (The Kodokan too).
This is true at least for the year 2014. Therefore you should always have
enough available cash on you. I always walked around with about 5000 JPY in my
wallet, and something like 30000 JPY in a hidden place, just in case. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are ATMs (To take money) at the convenience stores, and also at the post
bank. I only tried the convenience stores. I had a Mastercard and Visa cards,
and I could use both of them in the ATM of Seven Eleven (There is one on
Hakusan Dori. When you get out of the Kodokan, turn right and keep walking
until you see it). I think I could not use my cards at the ATM of Family Mart
and Lawson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Free time in Tokyo&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Training at the Kodokan is only 2 hours every day. You will have to sleep a lot
to recover (Sometimes even 10 hours), wash yourself and your laundry and take
care of the food. Still you end up with lots of free hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can use the free time to explore Tokyo. Tokyo is a city that is fun and
easy to explore. There is a very efficient subway system to get anywhere you
want in the city. There are also many interesting things to see. Describing
interesting things in Tokyo is beyond the scope of this article. I trust you to
research this subject yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you plan to experience the night life in Tokyo, you should know that the
subway does not work between 00:00 to about 5:30, and also that the Kodokan is
closed in those hours. If you are outside in this range of hours, you are on
your own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Walking around in Tokyo's Parks" src="http://www.newtolife.net/images/kodokan/tokyo_park.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Walking around in Tokyo's parks)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing that could be done with the free hours is work. If you want to
work in Tokyo, you will have to arrange a working visa ahead of time (I have
seen people who did that, but I have no idea how to do it. You should find out
yourself), and also find a place to work in Tokyo. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By what I have seen, I think that getting the working visa is the easy part.
Finding a place to work in Tokyo could be difficult if you don't speak
Japanese, and also if you don't plan to stay for a long time. Although
difficult, it is possible. I have met a few people that were staying in Japan
for a short period of time, working at special restaurants for example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you work internationally from a computer, you should know ahead of time
that free wifi is not very common in Tokyo. In many coffee shops, you will have
to bring the internet with you, by the means of a cellular wifi device. (As
mentioned before, you will find free wifi at the Kodokan hostel lobby, on the
3rd floor)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Injuries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are planning to practice every day at the Kodokan for a long period of
time, expect some injuries. I don't mean that you should be passimistic, I mean
that you should be ready. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Stuff from home&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find drugs and medicines in the Japanese pharmacies, however if you
don't know much Japanese, it could be hard to communicate what you are looking
for. It could also be expensive. Therefore if you have drugs or medicines from
home that you expect you are going to use, you should probably bring those with
you. (For example, anti-inflammatory drugs, heating lotions etc.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recommend you to use knee protectors, and bring with you other protectors
that you think you might use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Dealing with injuries at the Kodokan&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For light injuries, you can get lots of good tape both at the souvenir shop at
the entrance floor of the building, and also at the Do It Yourself shop right
next to the Kodokan. I think that one roll of tape costs 350-450 JPY.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also get ice inside a plastic bag at the Kodokan reception (They have
ice machine). If you want more ice, you can buy it at the convenice stores. (It
is originally made for drinks, but it will work for your injury too :) )&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you find yourself in bigger trouble, you will still be able to get help in
Tokyo. There are at least two pharmacies around the Kodokan, not very far away
(At least in 2014). The people who work there are really helpful, and with some
patience you will be able to communicate what you are after.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you need a doctor, there is a sports doctor (He practices at the Kodokan!)
right nearby. He is in the building at the intersection of Hakusan Dori and
Kasuga dori, about 2 minutes of walking from the Kodokan. I had a problem with
my shoulder and I went there to check it out. I paid a total of about 3000 JPY
for the doctor visit, which included xray, and special stickers to put on the
shoulder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Be smart on the mat&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can avoid many injuries by practicing correctly. Don't use much power, and
if your opponent demonstrates a good technique, let him throw you. You will not
be less of a person as a result. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing to remember is not to get on the mat if you are tired. Instead,
go to the 8th floor and watch the randori session from above. You can come
again fresh and sharp the next day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Getting to the Kodokan&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Contacting the International Department&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If by now you are convinced that you want to visit the Kodokan, the first
thing to do is to plan ahead your arrival time. Some times of the year might be
better than others. A good idea would be to send a mail to the International
Department (Could be found at the &lt;a href="http://www.kodokan.org"&gt;Kodokan website&lt;/a&gt;)
and ask. Just as an example - If you show up at the time of the summer course,
it could be both very hot and crowded. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After choosing a good time, send an email to the International Department about
2-3 months before your arrival, to reserve a bed at the Kodokan hostel. (If you
don't plan on staying at the Kodokan hostel, this is not necessary). The
International Department will ask you to fill a document with information about
yourself, and the estimated dates you plan to stay there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point all that is left is to show up. The first thing to do when you
get to the Kodokan is visit the International Department. You will pay for the
registration fee and the first training days. You will also get a Kodokan
membership card and a training card. The training card will be used at the
reception on the 4th floor, when you want to get into the dojo. You can also
recharge the card with more days at the 4th floor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Arrival instructions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two close airports - Haneda and Narita. Haneda is about 20-30 minutes
from the Kodokan, and Narita is about 2 hours. Basically you should get to
Kasuga station (Also known as Korakuen station) using the subway. The Kodokan
is right there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Hakusan dori and Kasuga dori
intersection" src="http://www.newtolife.net/images/kodokan/hakusan_dori.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Hakusan dori and Kasuga dori intersection. The Kodokan building is the gray
building next to the roller coaster.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What to bring&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I write here mostly the things that you might not think about yourself. (I'm
sure you will remember to bring your shirts and underwear)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Two passport images/kodokan&lt;/em&gt; Which will be used for your Kodokan training card.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Judogi from home.&lt;/em&gt; If you plan to practice daily, you will need more than
one Judogi. Two would be enough. (It could take a full day to dry a Judogi) If
you plan on buying a Judogi in Tokyo, you can bring only one Judogi from home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that in Tokyo you will find mostly Mizuno Judogis. Also note that Judogis
in Tokyo are not very cheap. A cheap Judogi (Jacket and Pants) could cost about
15000 JPY. With a Kodokan membership you can have about 20% discount.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A towel&lt;/em&gt; You don't get a towel at the Kodokan hostel, so you should bring your
own towel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A flashlight&lt;/em&gt; If you are going to stay at the dorms, a flashlight is going to
be useful. There could be many people in the dorms, and the light might be off
for long periods of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Medications, drugs, protectors (Knees, elbows), special tape&lt;/em&gt; Bring all the
things you usually use at home when you are injured. Be prepared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Running gear&lt;/em&gt; There are great places to run around Tokyo. Bring your sport
shoes and good pants if you are into running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Final personal Notes&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was really happy with my choice to visit the Kodokan. I experienced great
Judo. I will never fight the same. I also made some great friends. If you are a
Judoka, you really must check this place out. You will not regret it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thank the Kodokan team and my friends at the Kodokan for the great
experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally I hope that this document was of use to you.
Please send your thoughts to thenewtolife(&amp;amp;)outlook.com.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>